In this video, we are going to discuss the
contract change control system.
Now the contract change
control, very similar
to your regular integrated change control.
We are trying to properly control all of
the changes.
In integrated change
control, you're properly
controlling all changes to your project.
With the contract change control system is
specifically related to changes to the
contract, making sure you are properly
controlling all changes to the contract.
So contracts can be changed.
It's just that it has to be negotiated and
it has to be properly controlled.
So you're going to, I mean, the change
control system you used to track,
collect, communicate changes to the
contract.
It might be part of the regular change
control system.
The regular change control process as an
integrated change control, it might be
part of that, but it might be a separate
process.
Right.
Now, more than likely,
though, it's going to be a
separate process because
they're the third party involved.
Right.
And so generally, it's more complex.
So if you want to make a change to the
contract, right, it's a lot more difficult.
I want to say difficult, but it's more
challenging.
There's more procedures in place,
making changes to a contract, to a legal
contract, than there is to just some
internal procedures.
And then plus at the same time, there's
going to be a lot more back and forth.
because each party wants
to have a good understanding
of what the change is and
the reason for the change.
I want to make a change
to the functionality, me, the
buyer, I want to make a
change to the functionality.
The seller might not understand why,
and vice versa.
Seller wants to make a change to a
process.
I might not understand why.
So it's a little bit more complex here.
But contracts always need to be legally
amended.
right?
It always has to be the contract is a
legal document so it has to be legally
amended and that's where this whole
contract change control process I can't
let refers to it so you have to have a
proper change control process in place so
again in change control in generally the
project manager remember you are properly
controlling all changes to a
project you are not eliminating
all changes right you
are controlling all changes.
You are eliminating unnecessary changes.
You are only preventing unnecessary
changes to the project.
And so it's even more important when it
comes to the contract.
You want to make sure you
have a good proper change control
procedure in place when it
comes to changes to the contract.
Now let's talk about some of the common
types of contract changes, right?
Because some changes are going to involve,
you know, more procedures than others.
Some changes are simple.
Some changes are more complex.
So let's talk about the different types of
contract changes.
First and foremost,
which is the most common
type, admin changes,
administrative changes.
This is a very common type of
change to a contract where there
is no real adjustment to any
length, any timeline or payment.
right, it's not really, you know,
a huge major change, admin changes,
such as, for example, misspelling,
changes to personnel, right?
You just need to change your name.
So that doesn't necessarily need to go
through a whole legal process as such,
right, or something is misspelled,
a name is misspelled.
That doesn't really change the actual
contract itself.
It doesn't really change
the nature of the work or
the responsibilities of
the buyer and the seller.
However, this next one, the actual
contract modification, right?
That's another type of contract change.
So make sure you know these terms.
Administrative changes, contract
modification, supplemental agreement,
constructive changes, termination of
contract.
These are the common types of contract
changes.
So contract modification then,
this refers to actual substantive changes
to the contract, such as the actual
functionality of the work, or we need some
additional requirements, additional work,
right?
Or there's a change to the actual
timeline, change to the deadline.
So that would be, that would require a lot
of negotiation.
That's an actual change to the contract.
That would require legal modification
there.
Along with that, you've got something
called supplemental agreement.
Right.
So a supplemental agreement could be some
additional work.
It's negotiated separately.
Still part of the same contract.
Right.
Still part of the same work, part of the
same contract.
But it's just a separate negotiation.
Right.
Just for some additional work that we've
realized that we need.
to do but we don't need to
change the whole contract,
right, we're just a
supplemental agreement there.
Then we've got something called
constructive changes.
Now constructive changes is basically
purely from the action of the buyer,
the action or inaction of the buyer.
So for example, a perfect example here,
buyers not responding in time.
If the buyer doesn't respond in time,
that might push out the whole schedule.
Now the vendor should not be held liable.
But for that.
I mean, a lot of times they are, but they
should not really be held liable for that.
Right.
So, as a very simple example, let's say we
are, let's say, we're the vendor
organization, we are developing a website
for our customer.
And, you know, we've showed
them several examples, right,
we've gone back and forth
with some several examples.
And now, you know, there
are three or four options now,
right, for the homepage
and the flow of the website.
We've given them, you know, three or four
different options.
They need to choose.
one, right?
And they've told us that, you know,
they will tell us by this date.
And we've also said, you know,
if you tell us by this date, this
particular date, then we can meet the
deadline.
Now, we can meet the project deadline.
You need this entire website up and
running by this date.
Well, we need to know which of these
options you want, right?
By this date.
They don't get back to us by that date.
And then the next week,
the week after, for weeks we
don't hear back from We're
constantly following up.
And they keep saying, yeah, we'll get back
to you.
But they don't get back to us.
Well, that's not pushed out the data.
That's not pushed out the timeline.
We, if we're the vendor, we can't be,
we cannot be held liable for that, right?
So now we need to make a change to the
contract because of that.
Those changes are known as constructive
changes, right?
Because of the inaction of the buyer.
then you've got termination of the
contract and termination of the contract
is going to be covered in a separate video
there's several other terms that you need
to know regarding the termination of the
contract now claims administration what
happens if there's a dispute right all
right so there's always going to be
disputes right it's going to be
disagreements vendors and customers are
going to disagree with the work that's
performed and how it's performed and
what's delivered and so on and so on and
so forth.
But most of the time, vendors will
resolve.
Vendors and customer will resolve that
disagreement.
What happens if they don't?
All right.
So when the buyer and seller are
negotiating the contract, when they're
negotiating the contract, both buyer and
seller will be discussing.
If we have a dispute, if we
have a disagreement, this is
a procedure that we are
going to take to try and resolve.
that disagreement.
That procedure is documented in the
contract.
So the procedure for claims
administration is always
documented in the contract
or in the agreement itself.
This is one procedure, and
this is an exam tip here, this is
one procedure that is not
documented in a management plan.
So this procedure is not documented in the
procurement management plan.
This procedure is documented in the
contract itself, right?
So if we have a disagreement, you refer to
the contract.
This is how we're going to resolve the
disagreement.
Now, common areas of dispute, right?
So these are the four common areas that
PMI might ask about, right?
Warranty, right?
So the product or
service that the seller has
delivered, it's not doing
what it's supposed to do.
And so, you know, but it's within the
warranty period, they have to fix it.
Waiver means giving up certain rights,
one party giving up certain rights,
you know, each part here, one party giving
up the right to the other party.
Then we've got a breach of contract,
right?
Beach of contract basically refers to a
cardinal breach, right?
So, failure to meet the obligation,
right?
So again, this is going
to be covered in the, like
when we talk about the
closing of the contract.
So breach of contract then, so this refers
to failure to meet the contract.
This refers to termination,
early termination of
the contract, which is
covered in a separate video.
Then we've got cease and desist.
Cease and desist basically means stopping
some kind of illegal activity,
which is cease, and then desist,
not performing it again.
And a very common example of that for,
you know, let's say you're advertising
something and you're, you've got using an
artist's song in the background,
some piece of music in the background,
right?
from some famous artists, but you don't
have the permission to do that.
So the recording company or the artists
themselves may give you a cease and desist.
Stop using our song and don't do it again.
That's what cease and desist refers to.
Now, final settlements then, negotiated
settlements, final settlements for
outstanding claims and disputes,
right?
So that's what... So, Byron Seller
then, if there is a disagreement, right?
They come to a settlement, come to a
negotiation.
And that's really what that negotiated
settlement refers.
So, as a very simple example, you know,
the buyer owes the seller, I know,
$20,000.
But then because of the dispute and
everything, they're settled on $10,000.
Right, as long as the buyer pays them
$10,000, then, you know, that'll be fine.
Alternatively, there might be something
called ADR, the alternate dispute
resolution, right, if it cannot be
achieved through negotiation.
Again, this will be documented in the
contract as well, such as, for example,
mediation and arbitration.
So anyway, these are
just some contract change
control terms that you
need to be aware of.